A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Press Materials FA1322
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Record Group 1, Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078, 1951-2002; 1; 32.713 Cubic Feet 29 LTR size, 1 Half-LTR size, 44 LGL size, and 2 Half-LGL size Hollinger boxes and 1 oversize document box
  - Press releases, 1951-1975, 1990-1993; 1; 9.545 Cubic Feet About 1 half LGL size Hollinger box, 2 full LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 22 LTR size Hollinger boxes
    - News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 829-1005, 1972-1975; 3; 1.71 Cubic Feet About 4.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
      - 865. Educational finance and law, 1972 December 20 (Box 18, Folder 726)
      - 866. Memo to Education Editors and Writers, 1972 December (Box 18, Folder 727)
      - 867. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1972 December 26 (Box 18, Folder 728)
      - 868. Corporate Social Responsibility and the Institutional Investor, 1972-1973 (Box 18, Folder 729)
      - 869. Merrimon Cuninggim joining Ford Foundation, 1973 January 15 (Box 18, Folder 730)
      - 870. Symphonic Strains (Financial) reprint, 1973 February 1 (Box 18, Folder 731)
      - 871. History of grants in the State of Georgia, circa 1973 (Box 18, Folder 732)
      - 872. Memo to Urban and Legal Writers and Editors, 1973 January 31 (Box 18, Folder 733)
      - 873. Common problems in advanced industrial societies, 1973 February 21 (Box 18, Folder 734)
      - 874. Alternate lead for No. 873, 1973 February 21 (Box 18, Folder 735)
      - 875. Municipal conservation commissions, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 736)
      - 876. Connecticut alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 737)
      - 877. Maine alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 738)
      - 878. Massachusetts alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 739)
      - 879. New Hampshire alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 740)
      - 880. New Jersey alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 741)
      - 881. New York alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 742)
      - 882. Rhode Island alternate for No. 875, 1973 March 5 (Box 18, Folder 743)
      - 883. Annual Report - Poor countries, 1973 March 19 (Box 18, Folder 744)
      - 884. Public interest law, 1973 March 23 (Box 18, Folder 745)
      - 884. Soedjatmoko appointment to Ford Foundation Board of Trustees, 1973 April 2 (Box 18, Folder 746)
      - 885. Memo to Education Editors, Publishing Trade Press, and Others, circa 1973 (Box 18, Folder 747)
      - 886. History of grants in the State of California, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 748)
      - 887. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1973 April 13 (Box 19, Folder 749)
      - 888. Marshall A. Robinson, Earl F. Cheit, and Sanford M. Jaffe appointments, 1973 April 16 (Box 19, Folder 750)
      - 889. Sanford M. Jaffe appointment, 1973 April 16 (Box 19, Folder 751)
      - 890. History of grants in the State of Ohio, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 752)
      - 891. Memo to Urban, Financial, and Real Estate Writers and Editors, 1973 April 16 (Box 19, Folder 753)
      - 892. History of grants in the State of Texas, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 754)
      - 893. Community Development Corporations (CDCs), 1973 May 14 (Box 19, Folder 755)
      - 894. History of grants in the State of New Jersey, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 756)
      - 895. Leadership Development Program, 1973 May; File contains a group of still images related to the Ford Foundation Leadership Development Program. These images are stored on 3 individual pages and include captions. (Box 19, Folder 757)
      - 896. The Queen's University In Belfast, 1973 May 30 (Box 19, Folder 758)
      - 897. Building a New Generation of Arms Control Analysts, 1973 April-June (Box 19, Folder 759)
        File also contains a Memo to Urban, Financial, and Real Estate Writers and Editors about urban housing.
      - 898. Memo to Editors - Mexican Americans, 1973 June 10 (Box 19, Folder 760)
      - 899. An Inquiry into the Uses of Instructional Technology, 1973 June 25 (Box 19, Folder 761)
      - 900. History of grants in the State of Arizona, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 762)
      - 901. The Arena Stage in Washington, D.C., 1973 July 9 (Box 19, Folder 763)
      - 902. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1973 July 10 (Box 19, Folder 764)
      - 903. Memo on minority contractors, 1973 July; File contains a set of three untitled still images related to minority contractor association groups. The images are stored on three different pages and include captions. (Box 19, Folder 765)
      - 904. Venture Fund, 1973 July 24 (Box 19, Folder 766)
      - 905. The Ford Foundation and Public Broadcasting, 1973 August 23 (Box 19, Folder 767)
      - 906. Indonesia oral history program, 1973 August 31 (Box 19, Folder 768)
      - 907. Special Report: Economic Muscle for La Raza, 1973 September 15 (Box 19, Folder 769)
      - 908. Minority graduate fellowships, 1973 October 1 (Box 19, Folder 770)
      - 909. International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT - Centro International de Agricultura Tropical), 1973 October 3 (Box 19, Folder 771)
      - 910. The Future of the International Economic Order, 1973 October 22 (Box 19, Folder 772)
      - 911. Robert H. Edwards appointment, circa 1973 October (Box 19, Folder 773)
      - 912. Marshall A. Robinson appointment, circa 1973 October (Box 19, Folder 774)
      - 913. Grants for Research on Population Issues Announced, circa 1973 (Box 19, Folder 775)
      - 914. Minorities and Public Television, 1973 October (Box 19, Folder 776)
      - 915. Special Report: The Real World of Lawyering, 1973 December (Box 19, Folder 777)
      - 916. Peter E. de Janosi and James T. Ivy appointments, circa 1973 December (Box 19, Folder 778)
      - 917. Ford Motor Company stock disposition, 1973 December 17 (Box 19, Folder 779)
      - 918. Research in reproductive biology, 1974 January 7 (Box 19, Folder 780)
      - 919. Grants in 1973 to Greece, 1974 January 3 (Box 19, Folder 781)
      - 920. Harold Howe II testimony to the U.S. Senate on the status of women, 1973 October 17 (Box 19, Folder 782)
      - 922. 1973 Annual Report, 1974 March 24 (Box 19, Folder 783)
      - 923. Marshall A. Robertson excerpts from 1973 Annual Report, 1974 March 24 (Box 19, Folder 784)
      - 924. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Exploring Energy Choices, 1974 March 31 (Box 19, Folder 785)
      - 925. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1974 March-April (Box 19, Folder 786)
      - 926. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Nuclear Theft: Risks and Safeguards, 1974 April 7 (Box 20, Folder 787)
      - 927. Public interest law firms, 1974 April 15 (Box 20, Folder 788)
      - 928. Tutorial Community Project - Tomorrow We'll See What Happens, 1974 April 22 (Box 20, Folder 789)
      - 929. Special Report: Farming Arid Lands, 1974 May 1 (Box 20, Folder 790)
      - 930. History of grants in the State of Oregon, circa 1974 (Box 20, Folder 791)
      - 931. Grants to Public Television Station Program Cooperative, 1974 May 22 (Box 20, Folder 792)
      - 932. History of grants in the State of Alabama, circa 1974 (Box 20, Folder 793)
      - 933. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Rehabilitation Potential of Western Coal Lands, 1974 June 3 (Box 20, Folder 794)
      - 934. History of grants in the State of Colorado, circa 1974 (Box 20, Folder 795)
      - 935. Council on Library Resources, 1974 June 14 (Box 20, Folder 796)
      - 936. State and local government productivity, 1974 June 27 (Box 20, Folder 797)
      - 937. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Oil Spills and the Marine Environment, 1974 June 28 (Box 20, Folder 798)
      - 938. Venture Fund, 1974 July 8 (Box 20, Folder 799)
      - 939. Research program on the finances of the performing arts, 1974 August 6 (Box 20, Folder 800)
      - 940. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy Prices, 1974 August 12 (Box 20, Folder 801)
      - 941. Population and Development: Is a Consensus Possible?, 1974 August 15 (Box 20, Folder 802)
      - 942. Minority Enrollment and Representation in Institutions of Higher Education, 1974 August 26 (Box 20, Folder 803)
      - 943. Energy Policy Program (EPP) - Energy Taxes and Subsidies, 1974 August 30 (Box 20, Folder 804)
      - 944. Faculty fellowships for research on the roll of women in society, 1974 September 5 (Box 20, Folder 805)
      - 945. Common problems in industrial societies, 1974 September 18 (Box 20, Folder 806)
      - 946. Masters of Choice, 1974 September 25 (Box 20, Folder 807)
      - 947. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1974 September 27 (Box 20, Folder 808)
      - 948. Visual arts - support for artists, 1974 September 29 (Box 20, Folder 809)
      - 949. Andrew F. Brimmer election to Ford Foundation Board of Trustees, 1974 September 29 (Box 20, Folder 810)
      - 950. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Financing the Energy Industry, 1974 October 4 (Box 20, Folder 811)
      - 951. Employment in the Developing Nations, 1974 October 15 (Box 20, Folder 812)
      - 952. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - A Time to Choose, 1974 October 18 (Box 20, Folder 813)
      - 953. New Life for Old Neighborhoods, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 814)
      - 954. Problems and Issues Concerning Vietnam Veterans, Deserters, ad Draft-Evaders, 1974 September-October (Box 20, Folder 815)
      - 955. The Art of Managing the Environment, 1974 September-October (Box 20, Folder 816)
      - 956. International Council of Bayoud Research, 1974 November 1; File contains two sets of two untitled still images related to the study of date palms and bayoud disease in the Sahara desert region. Images include captions. (Box 20, Folder 817)
      - 957. Law and justice, 1974 November 6 (Box 20, Folder 818)
      - 958. Schools, Taxes, and Voter Behavior, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 819)
      - 959. Program Related Investments (PRI), 1974 November 12 (Box 20, Folder 820)
      - 960. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy Consumption in Manufacturing, 1974 November 26 (Box 20, Folder 821)
      - 961. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Potential Fuel Effectiveness in Industry, 1974 November 26 (Box 20, Folder 822)
      - 962. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Perspective on Power, 1974 November 27 (Box 20, Folder 823)
      - 963. Bellagio Conference Papers, 1974 December 15 (Box 20, Folder 824)
      - 964. Ford Foundation Board of Trustees statement - Expenditures, 1974 December 14 (Box 20, Folder 825)
      - 965. Resources for the Future program (RFF), 1974 December 31 (Box 20, Folder 826)
      - 966. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy and U.S. Foreign Policy, 1975 January 3 (Box 20, Folder 827)
      - 967. International economic research, 1975 January 27 (Box 20, Folder 828)
      - 968. Richard C. Sheldon appointment, 1975 January 27 (Box 20, Folder 829)
      - 969. History of grants in the State of Louisiana, circa 1975 (Box 20, Folder 830)
      - 970. History of grants in the State of Illinois, circa 1975 (Box 20, Folder 831)
      - 971. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1975 February 11 (Box 20, Folder 832)
      - 972. History of grants in the State of New York, circa 1975 (Box 20, Folder 833)
      - 973. Recording-Publication Program, 1975 March 3 (Box 21, Folder 834)
      - 974. International Women's Year Tribune, 1975 March 24 (Box 21, Folder 835)
      - 975. Venture Fund termination, 1974-1975 (Box 21, Folder 836)
      - 976. History of grants in the State of Pennsylvania, circa 1975 (Box 21, Folder 837)
        Contents may have been moved to Series 1, Subseries 3, File: 987. History of grants in the State of Pennsylvania, 1975 (Folder 848).
      - 977. 1974 Annual Report, 1975 March 31 (Box 21, Folder 838)
      - 978. Upcoming Reports press calendar, 1975 May 5 (Box 21, Folder 839)
      - 979. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Competition in the U.S. Energy Industry, 1975 May 6 (Box 21, Folder 840)
      - 980. Note to Editors - Women's Resource Center, 1975 May-July (Box 21, Folder 841)
      - 981. Note to Editors - Research conference, 1975 May 28 (Box 21, Folder 842)
      - 982. Energy Policy Project (EPP) -New Energy Technology for Buildings, 1975 June 2 (Box 21, Folder 843)
      - 983. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy Research and Development, 1975 June 9 (Box 21, Folder 844)
      - 984. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy Conservation Papers, 1975 June 16 (Box 21, Folder 845)
      - 985. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - The American Energy Consumer, 1975 June 30 (Box 21, Folder 846)
      - 986. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Energy and Agriculture in the Third World, 1975 July 7 (Box 21, Folder 847)
      - 987. History of grants in the State of Pennsylvania, circa 1975 (Box 21, Folder 848)
      - 988. History of grants in the State of Indiana, circa 1975 (Box 21, Folder 849)
      - 989. Energy Policy Project (EPP) - Industry Perspectives, undated (Box 21, Folder 850)
      - 990. Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC), undated (Box 21, Folder 851)
      - 991. Housing, 1975 September 9 (Box 21, Folder 852)
      - 992. Energy vs. environment, 1975 September 22 (Box 21, Folder 853)
      - 993. Research for world economic relations, 1975 September 25 (Box 21, Folder 854)
      - 994. Greek grants, 1975 June 4 (Box 21, Folder 855)
      - 995. Harvey P. Hall death, 1975 June 19 (Box 21, Folder 856)
      - 996. Refugee grants, 1975 July 25 (Box 21, Folder 857)
      - 997. Special Report: The Quality of Working Life, 1975 September-October (Box 21, Folder 858)
      - 998. Reporters and Editors - Mexican American grants, 1975 October 10 (Box 21, Folder 859)
      - 999. Hedley Donovan election to Ford Foundation Board of Trustees, 1975 October 16 (Box 21, Folder 860)
      - 1000 Memo to Urban Affairs Editors and Writers - Integrateducation, 1975 July 2 (Box 21, Folder 861)
      - 1001. Ford Foundation assistance to Puerto Ricans, 1975 November 12 (Box 21, Folder 862)
      - 1002. Indochina Fellowship Awards, 1975 November 13 (Box 21, Folder 863)
      - 1003. Grants for scholarship on Soviet Union and East Europe, 1975 November 24 (Box 21, Folder 864)
      - 1004. Memo to Editors - Remarks by Basil Whiting, 1975 November 24 (Box 21, Folder 865)
      - 1005. Vietnam War veteran clemency, 1975 December 16 (Box 21, Folder 866)
    - Press release job files, 1990-1993; 4; 1.035 Cubic Feet About .25 LTR size Hollinger box and 2 LGL size Hollinger boxes
      Subseries contains the job files for a number of Ford Foundation press releases created between 1990 and 1993. Instead of just including copies of published press releases (and sometimes supplementary documents) like the files in the first three subseries of Series 1, the files in this subseries provide evidence of the processes that edited, publicized, and disseminated the finished news announcements. Materials such as press release drafts, correspondence, invoices, contracts with publicity services, media outlet mailing lists, printing instructions, and package tracking forms help document these activities.
      Job files are identified by the job numbers listed in the file names. Both the Ford Foundation Office of Reports and Office of Communications appear to have helped create the files. Closer analysis of the subseries materials may better reveal the relationship between the two entities.
      - 90-06. Race Relations and Campus Diversity, 1990 January-April (Box 21, Folder 867)
      - 90-08. New Trustee David T. Kearns, 1990 April (Box 21, Folder 868)
      - 90-09. Alternative arts organizations, 1990 April-May (Box 21, Folder 869)
      - 90-14. Innovations in State and Local Government Awards Program 1990 finalists, 1990 June-October (Box 22, Folder 870)
      - 90-18. Race Relations and Campus Diversity - Announcement of winners, 1990 February-December (Box 22, Folder 871-872)
      - 90-23. Fellowships and internships in international law, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 873)
      - 90-22. Arms control and peacemaking, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 874)
      - 90-26. Grants to strengthen community college, 1990 November-December (Box 22, Folder 875)
      - 90-27. Community foundations, 1990-1991 (Box 22, Folder 876-877)
      - 91-13. Innovations in State and Local Government Awards Program 1991 winners, 1991-1992 (Box 22, Folder 878-881)
      - 91-17. New Trustee Luis Nogales, 1991 July (Box 23, Folder 882)
      - 91-18. Lloyd Garrison named Director of Communications, 1991 July-August (Box 23, Folder 883)
      - 91-19. Black and Hispanic art museums, 1991 August-September (Box 23, Folder 884-885)
      - 91-26. New Trustee Robert D. Haas, 1991-1992 (Box 23, Folder 886)
      - 91-24b. Innovations in State and Local Government Awards Program 1992 finalists, 1991-1992 (Box 23, Folder 887-888)
      - 91-24c. Innovations in State and Local Government Awards Program 1992 winners, 1992 July (Box 23, Folder 889)
      - 92-07. New Director of Education and Culture Program Alison Bernstein, 1992 March-May (Box 23, Folder 890)
      - 92-09. Joan A. Dassin named Director of Latin America and Caribbean Programs, 1992 September-October (Box 23, Folder 891)
      - 92-13. Advisory group on United Nations financing, 1992 September-December (Box 23, Folder 892)
      - 92-21. David D. Arnold named Representative of New Delhi Field Office, 1992 September-December (Box 23, Folder 893)
      - 92-22. New World Demands New Approach to United Nations Funding, 1993 February 23 (Box 23, Folder 894)
      - 92-23. New Chairman of Board of Trustees Henry B. Schacht, 1992 December; File contains one still image titled "Henry B. Schacht". (Box 23, Folder 895)
        According to the original folder, this press release was cancelled.
      - 92-25. Linda B. Strumpf named Ford Foundation Vice President, 1992 December (Box 23, Folder 896)
  - Press clippings, 1964-2002; 2; 21.271 Cubic Feet About 40 LGL size Hollinger boxes, 6 LTR size Hollinger boxes, and 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger box
    The series was broken into four subseries during processing in order to represent identified systems of organization found within the record group as well as to facilitate improved user access to the large number of files encompassed by the series. The first three subseries comprise the record group's total amount of original press clippings selected by Burrelle's Information Services and Luce Press Clippings for the Ford Foundation. In contrast, the fourth subseries consists of bound collections of press clipping photocopies prepared by the Ford Foundation Office of Reports.
    Box contents and sequential relationships between record group containers did not reveal a uniform system of arrangement imposed by the records' creators for the original Burrelle's and Luce press clippings. Original order has been maintained in this regard, so users will find that files within the first three subseries are not in chronological order and that files concerning the same subject or program area are not all grouped together. Nevertheless, the creation of subseries based primarily on the original box numbers and groupings did highlight discrete patterns of arrangement that the Ford Foundation Office of Communications and the other entities involved in the creation/custodianship of the records must have used. These patterns likely represent evolving trends in how the records' creators organized the press clippings over time as well as conscious decisions the creators made when deciding what files to group together in the boxes.
    Series 2. Subseries 1. Clippings, announcements, and miscellaneous press media, 1964-1998
    Series is comprised of three main types of documents: 1) original press clippings collected by Burelle's Information Services and Luce Press Clippings for the Ford Foundation; 2) announcements transmitted to the Ford Foundation by Burrelle's and Luce about press mentions of the Foundation; and 3) various issues of the Comment on the Ford Foundation publication. The first two types make up Subseries 1, 2, and 3 of Series 2 while the third type makes up Subseries 4.
    Burrelle's and Luce were external press clipping services that monitored newspapers and other types of print media for references to the Ford Foundation. The announcements they transmitted to the Ford Foundation were called Burrelle's NewsExpress and Luce AM Newsbreak respectively. Materials at the end of Series 2 Subseries 3 discuss a software program called Burrelle's Information Office (BIO) that likely changed how the Ford Foundation received its press clipping services during the early 2000s.
    Press clips are identified by the tags that the different clipping service providers stuck to them. They detail the name of the newspaper, the date of the article, and the name of the clipping service. Clips were organized into files in order to document news coverage on certain programs, individuals, and topics. Programs like Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Education, Media, Arts, and Culture (EMAC), Asset Building and Community Development (ASSETS), and Innovations in American Government Awards have the most amount of files devoted to their news coverage. Prominently featured individuals in the series include Ford Foundation Presidents McGeorge Bundy, Franklin Thomas, and Susan Berresford. There are also a number of files that contain miscellaneous mentions of the Ford Foundation.
    In addition to clippings and announcements, the first three subseries contain press logs, correspondence, and internal memoranda as well as some press media material like speeches and press releases.
    The Comment on the Ford Foundation publications are bound collections of press clipping photocopies that provided news coverage on the Ford Foundation's activities for a specific period of time or in relation to a specific subject.
    - Clippings, announcements, and miscellaneous press media, 1964-1998; 1; 2.35 Cubic Feet About 5 LGL size Hollinger boxes
      The 1996-1998 press clippings derive from the same period as the clippings in Series 2 Subseries 2 and in Series 2 Subseries 3. Several miscellaneous press clipping files are included as they are in the aforementioned subseries, and Series 2 Subseries 1 also includes several files housing press clippings related to the Innovations in American Government Awards Program like the other two subseries. However, the Innovations files in this subseries have a more specific focus than the other Innovations files. File names indicate topical themes such as arts and education. Another organizational difference between the 1996-1998 press clipping files in Series 2 Subseries 1 and their counterparts in the latter two subseries centers around the files' lack of program focus. The Innovations in American Government Awards Program is the only Ford Foundation program featured in the arrangement scheme of Subseries 1 whereas many of the press clippings in Subseries 2 and Subseries 3 are grouped together based on program area.
      The 1977-1982 and 1965-1972 press clipping files in Subseries 1 originate from earlier time periods than the files in Subseries 2 and 3 that only house clippings from the 1990s and early 2000s. These files chiefly concern the topics of Ford Foundation Presidents Franklin Thomas and McGeorge Bundy, the new Ford Foundation headquarters building in New York City, and the United Nations Development Corporation. Files related to Franklin Thomas actually hold other types of material besides press clippings. They include speeches, magazines, and press releases as well.
      The subseries also houses a file containing faxes from the Ford Foundation Office of Communications to the Chronicle of Philanthropy magazine company. These faxes originate from the early 1990s.
      - Relinking Life and Work: Toward a Better Future - Not circulated, 1997-1998 (Box 24, Folder 897)
      - Innovations in American Government Awards Program, 1997-1998 (Box 24, Folder 898)